<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at Harley in Shropshire, December 2. 1697. Being the day of publick thanksgiving for the peace; and for His Majesty's safe return. By Ben. Jenks, rector of Harley, and chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of Bradford.</title>
            <author>Jenks, Benjamin, 1646-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46790</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825501</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825501</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29883</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46790)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29883)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1761:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at Harley in Shropshire, December 2. 1697. Being the day of publick thanksgiving for the peace; and for His Majesty's safe return. By Ben. Jenks, rector of Harley, and chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of Bradford.</title>
                  <author>Jenks, Benjamin, 1646-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Will. Rogers, at the Sun against St. Dunstan's Church; and Benj. Tooke, at the Middle-Temple-Gate in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXCVII. [1697]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A thanksgiving-sermon for the peace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29883:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D AT HARLEY in SHROPSHIRE, DECEMBER 2. 1697. BEING THE <hi>Day of Publick Thankſgiving</hi> For the PEACE; AND FOR His Majeſty's Safe Return.</p>
            <p>By BEN. JENKS, Rector of <hi>Harley,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Bradford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> againſt St. <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan</hi>'s Church; and <hi>Benj. Cooke,</hi> at the <hi>Middle-Temple-Gate</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_publisher">
            <pb facs="tcp:29883:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29883:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PUBLISHER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU ſhew the Power that you have with me, To put me upon expoſing my Weakneſs more than once or twice: And, for ought I know, in a greater meaſure now than formerly: This being ſuch a Sudden Production, upon a Subject that never Exercis'd my Thoughts before; Peradventure it may not obtain my own Pardon a while hence. Yet I was the more inclinable to Comply with your Requeſt for my Notes, Becauſe through your means, I had my Hand in ſo early, juſt as his moſt Excellent Majeſty was Aſcending the Throne: For which Zeal and Forwardneſs, ſome have not yet Forgot to look as much Awry at me, as <hi>Eliab</hi> did at his Brother <hi>David, 1 Sam. 17.28.</hi> And now that King <hi>WILLIAM</hi>'s Throne is ſo eſtabliſh'd by this Glorious Peace, to Rejoice the Souls of his Friends, and to ſtrike Deſpair into the Hearts of his
<pb facs="tcp:29883:3"/>Enemies; If you will make theſe Overflowings of my Joy and Gladneſs for ſo rich a Bleſſing to our Church and Nation, more Diffuſive than the narrow Bounds wherein I am concern'd, The mean defective Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon may come Behind, as a little Servitor, to Wait upon thoſe Many much more Worthy, that are like to be Publiſh'd upon ſuch a great and Joyful Occaſion. I leave you and your Friends to do as you pleaſe, by it and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your — <hi>B. J.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29883:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH LII. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How Beautiful upon the Mountains are the Feet of him that bringeth good Tidings, that publiſheth Peace, that bringeth Good Tidings of Good, that publiſheth Salvation, that ſaith unto <hi>Zion,</hi> Thy God Reigneth!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD News in bad Times is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Refreſhment. And after we have long been Complaining of the <hi>Times,</hi> Now that we are called to Rejoice in the <hi>News;</hi> After we have been Tir'd out with a tedious <hi>War,</hi> to be Eas'd at laſt: This is ſo Grateful and Pleaſant to every one who has any Concern for his own, or his Country's Welfare; That the Meſſengers of ſuch <hi>Glad Tidings,</hi> who uſe to be received with Tranſports of Joy, may look to be Careſs'd with all the Demonſtrations of good Welcome. And therefore I need not beg your patient Audience, Beloved, when I can promiſe my ſelf your Eager At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: Now that we are to give Thanks for the Accompliſhment of ſomewhat here Propheſied; And the <hi>Tidings of Good,</hi> the Publications of <hi>Peace,</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told to the <hi>Church,</hi> are come to our <hi>Land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> What we have ſo long Deſired, The God of all grace has let us Live to ſee it Effected; Even <hi>Peace in our Time,</hi> after ſo many Burdens and Miſchiefs of War, and a happy Cloſe of the <hi>Bloody Scene;</hi> Upon Terms of Honour to our Government, and terms of Security to our Church: Upon a mighty Stoop on the Adverſe Side, and a total Excluſion of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Intereſt, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29883:4"/>Alarm'd our Fears. Now that the biggeſt of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad have publickly Owned him for <hi>King</hi> of this Realm, whom the little Bigots at Home have all this while ſtood out againſt; Animated with hopes of Help from that <hi>Foreign</hi> Power, which has ſhaken them off, and left the Forlorn Cauſe to ſhift for it ſelf: The Throne is no longer threatned now with an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion</hi> from that Quarter, whence the Struggle was ſo hard, not only to Change our Laws, but to Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate our Religion. And to have our moſt Deſired <hi>Prince</hi> come back in Safety from (we hope) the <hi>Laſt</hi> Expedition of this kind; To have our Eaſy Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firm upon the ancient <hi>Baſis</hi> of its Limited Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy: Our Religion Preſerv'd and Protected, and our <hi>Peace</hi> Reſtor'd and Ratified; This is Reviving indeed, even as Life from the Dead, to a drooping Nation. And ſuch is the Matter of Joy and Praiſe, wherein we are called to take our ſhare at this time.</p>
            <p>But as great as ever the preſent Gladneſs of our Land is, The <hi>Text</hi> will lead us up to a higher Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing yet, for a greater Salvation than any that can be Conſummated in this World; and for a <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Amity</hi> beyond and above the ſtricteſt League and deareſt Friendſhip with all the Creatures upon Earth. For under <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Deliverance here out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> is figured the Glory and Proſperity of the <hi>Church,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd by our Lord Jeſus. And the Text is a joyful Exclamation upon the Bleſſed Occaſion; Shewing how Acceptable to the People of God, that Wait for his Salvation, is the Church's Welfare, and Peace upon <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For then is the Joy of the Church moſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, When Darkneſs and Wickedneſs are moſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiered; When not only Peace and a Worldly Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> do Prevail and Flouriſh. <hi>How Beautiful upon the Mountains,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29883:4"/>
            <p>Mount <hi>Zion</hi> ſupported the famous Temple, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting all the Church: And <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which it ſtood, being ſurrounded with Hills, The Prophet here in a <hi>Rapture</hi> breaks out, as if he had ſeen a Meſſenger coming upon thoſe High Places, to bring Tidings of Joy, to the <hi>City of God.</hi> For on the adjacent Hills, in the Cliffs and Rocks, they had <hi>Watchmen,</hi> upon any Diſcovery of Danger or Proſperity, to give Signals; whereupon Poſts were diſpatch'd, to haſte away o're the Hills, and tell the News. And their Feet here, (denoting their Advent, or their Haſte) are called <hi>Beautiful;</hi> To ſhew how Welcome they were, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon a Joyful Errand. Though the <hi>Feet,</hi> in a Meſſenger uſe to be leaſt Comely, as cover'd o're with Duſt or Dirt: Yet ſo Grateful are they, when bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us News to our Wiſhes, that we count 'em all over <hi>Lovely;</hi> and are ready to kiſs the <hi>Feet</hi> of them that come to us with the Glad Tidings of great Joy. And O what greater Good than that deſigned here in this Text under the names of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> with the Publication of both to <hi>Zion;</hi> and both compriz'd in this Meſſage to be told her, <hi>Thy God Reigneth!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He does indeed <hi>Reign</hi> always; Though the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Rage, and people imagine Vain things; and though Kings and Rulers of the Earth Conſult and Bandy againſt him and his <hi>Chriſt;</hi> Even when things go moſt Croſs and Diſorderly, ſtill he holds the <hi>Reins</hi> of the World's Government: and 'tis his Permiſſion and Pleaſure, there ſhould be <hi>Miſconduct</hi> ſometimes, and Havock made even upon the Sheep of his Paſture; for Wiſe and holy Ends, known to Himſelf. And at ſuch times of Confuſion and Trouble to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God ſtands by, as if he left ill Men to do what they would, and Carry all before 'em; As if he withdrew, and had nothing to do in the matter.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:29883:5"/>
            <p>For there's a Kingdom of <hi>Satan</hi> and of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and the Enemies of our Lord have their Allotted Time, to Reign as Lords of the World. But God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, It is but a <hi>Short</hi> Time, till they ſhall be made his <hi>Footſtool;</hi> and brought under the narroweſt Reſtraint, and Everlaſting Contempt. Yea, even in the mean time, He Ruleth in the Very midſt of his <hi>Enemies;</hi> whom he has in Inviſible Chains, and makes even their Serpentine Enmity, as the <hi>Rod</hi> of his Anger, and the <hi>Staff</hi> of his Indignation; to ſerve the purpoſes of his Glory: Though they neither know nor mean any ſuch thing as the Execution of his Pleaſure.</p>
            <p>But when again he Reveals his Arm to Break the Oppoſer's Forces, To Gather his diſperſed Flock, and to Raiſe up his dejected People; Then he is ſaid to <hi>Reign</hi> in eſpecial manner. Then he eminently Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers his Supremacy, and his Over-Ruling Hand, to take the Immediate Care of his <hi>Own;</hi> To Cultivate his <hi>Vine,</hi> and to make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a Praiſe in the whole Earth; Reſcuing his Servants out of the hands of <hi>Ill Maſters,</hi> to Keep and Bleſs, to Guide and Proſper them Himſelf. Now this the Lord did in the Deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> here foretold, out of their Captivity: This he did in the greater Deliverance, wrought by our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Coming into the World: This he has done in many Deliverances of his Church, ſince that time; whereof we of this Church have had frequent and Remarkable Experience: (O how much is yet freſh and Lively in our Remembrance!) And this he will do yet more Wonderfully, than all, in the <hi>Later days,</hi> towards the End of Time; when he ſhall come to Accompliſh all the precious Promiſes, that raiſe the Hopes of Believers: When Righteouſneſs and Light and Love ſhall there Proſper and Reign; Where now Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Ungodlineſs and Diſcord bear Sway and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29883:5"/>Abound. O Bleſſed Time! Enough to excite all that wiſh well to <hi>Sion,</hi> to Pray as our Church teaches us, and beſeech God to <hi>Haſten his Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Text looking further than the Buſineſs of this Day, I muſt not <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderlook</hi> the great Deſign of ſuch a place; any more than I muſt <hi>Overlook</hi> the Occaſion of our preſent Meeting. This is now Joyful to us all: And if the other be not ſo too, The fault is our own; that we are in no better Temper, to Reſent the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Mercies of God; and to Praiſe him for his Chriſt, and for his Goſpel, and all things conducing to help us on to his Heavenly <hi>Kingdom;</hi> As well as to give him Thanks for the Temporal Good of this <hi>World;</hi> and for ſome Eaſier and Better Time, that we hope to have in it. For this, without the other, will do us no real Kindneſs at all, nor make us any thing happier at the Laſt. And, alas, <hi>Sirs,</hi> How can the <hi>Rebels</hi> againſt God, ever be <hi>Hearty</hi> in their Thanks to him? O what Senſe is there in it, for ſuch as do nothing but Confront and Reſiſt his Word, to come into the Aſſemblies of thoſe that meet for his Worſhip! For ſuch as make the <hi>Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring</hi> of God even their Buſineſs, to make any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of giving him the <hi>Glory</hi> due to his Name! And if that which ſhould Heighten the Joy of this Day, do (in their eſteem) but ſerve to caſt a <hi>Damp</hi> upon it; I cannot help this: Unleſs I ſhould handle the Word of God Deceitfully, to Preach <hi>Peace</hi> where there is none; Or to Flatter and Collogue with thoſe, who will ſtill be the Enemies of our <hi>Peace,</hi> becauſe the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our <hi>God.</hi> They that Scorn the very <hi>Goſpel</hi> of Peace, and Stomach ſuch as bring thoſe Gladdeſt of all Tidings, are fitter for another Service, than religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to Obſerve a <hi>Thankſgiving-Day,</hi> in a Chriſtian Congregation, among the Followers of <hi>Jeſus.</hi> O that they were but once Fallen out with their ſcandalous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29883:6"/>Sins, and better Friends to their own Souls! And then they might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear of <hi>Peace</hi> with God, and come to ſee the Joy of his Salvation.</p>
            <p>But I will ſpeak Firſt of that which now lies upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt upon all our Thoughts; The Good Tidings of Good things, in the Publication of That <hi>Peace,</hi> which we are at this time to Thank the Lord our God for ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us, by the hands of his Choſen Meſſenger, whom he rais'd up, and has Preſerv'd and Proſper'd, to bring us at laſt ſo great a Bleſſing. And inſtead of Grumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that we had it no <hi>Sooner,</hi> when our own Sins kept it from us ſo Long; O how ſhould we Admire and Magnify the Gracious God, that we have <hi>at all,</hi> the Comfortable Privilege; which, he knows, is none of our Deſert, but the meer Gift of his own Mercy!</p>
            <p>Now the Good of this <hi>Peace,</hi> and wherein we are the Better for it, The joyous Conſequences will beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us: But to raiſe our Thankfulneſs at this time to ſome higher Pitch, I will offer a few faint Strokes at the Lovely Picture; in ſhewing both the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſineſs</hi> from which it frees us; and alſo the <hi>Advantages</hi> which it brings us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>neaſineſs</hi> which this Peace frees us from. Though all the Burthen of <hi>Taxes</hi> be not preſently Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; yet we have the fair Proſpect of <hi>Mitigation;</hi> and good ground to Hope, That we may ſoon find the Load made Lighter; and that the Effect will ceaſe, when the Cauſe is taken away. But O how great is the Eaſe to our Minds, to be delivered from the Danger and Dread of our <hi>Enemies!</hi> From a Potent Enemy at our Doors, that was the Back to all our Enemies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Doors; which made 'em ſo Brisk and Daring, to Affront the Higheſt Authority; and Threaten the faithful Subjects to Suffer even for their Fidelity. But now the Horns of thoſe <hi>Malecontents,</hi> that were but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29883:6"/>Short before, are quite Cut off; that which Fed them, being ſubſtracted from them. And the <hi>Peace</hi> may prove the beſt <hi>Phyſick</hi> to Purge out theſe Malignant Humours, that have made them ſo Troubleſome hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Now their Hopes from <hi>Abroad</hi> muſt give up the Ghoſt, and all their Expectation periſh. While we have the ſatisfaction to ſee their wretched Cauſe Cruſh'd and Ruin'd; and themſelves put out of Capacity, to give us the Vexation, and to do us the Miſchief which ſo fain they would.</p>
            <p>'Tis a painful State, to live in perpetual Concern and Fear of Subtile, Mighty, and Malicious <hi>Foes,</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Wait to Invade and Over-run us; and not only to fetch out ſuch large Gaps, as have been made in our Eſtates, to Maintain the Charge of the <hi>War;</hi> But to ſweep away all from us, and not ſuffer our ſelves nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Survive</hi> and ſtay behind. To have our Thoughts ſtill on the Stretch, and our Minds Rack'd with continual Devices, how to Offend our Enemies, or Defend our ſelves, is ſuch an Irkſome Life, as is enough to make us Weary of Living: When we go ſo Gall'd under the Sharps, the Cares, and Frights, that ſurround and grate upon us; To <hi>Fear continually, becauſe of the Fury of the Oppreſſor, as if he were ready to deſtroy,</hi> Iſa. 51.13. And this was ſpoke for the Conſolation of a people haraſs'd and wearied with the Plagues of <hi>War,</hi> Mich. 4.4. That they ſhould <hi>ſit every man under his Vine, and every man under his Figtree, and none ſhould make 'em Afraid.</hi> Our Fear was of Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to take away not only our Laws, our Liberties and Properties, but our Religion and our Lives. We went in Jeopardy of New Lords, that would have left us no Choice, but <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Martyrdom.</hi> But the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>League</hi> has rid our Breaſts of thoſe Apprehenſions: Becauſe it Secludes him that pretends a <hi>Right</hi> to Enſlave
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29883:7"/>us; and Enervates his Hopes of playing an After-Game. And this very <hi>Eaſe</hi> to our Minds, Beloved, Is it not better than Thouſands of Gold and Silver? To have our Affairs put in ſuch a Setled Poſture, that we are not like to Out-live the bleſſed Advantages which we have for our Souls; That we do not go with our <hi>Lives</hi> in our hands; and that which ſhould be Dearer to us all than our Lives, Tottering and ready to tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble down; That the Noiſes of <hi>Guns</hi> and <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> which were like the hideous Shrieks of the Dying, or as hollow Groans, and aſtoniſhing Roarings from the Dead; Are become now <hi>Muſick</hi> in our ears, and only the <hi>Symbols</hi> and Expreſſes of our Feſtivity and Rejoycing: This is a Change, whereof we cannot but be Glad: And O that we may acknowledge it, with ſuch a Grateful Senſe as we ought, to the Lord our God! O that we may abound in his <hi>Praiſe,</hi> who has Eas'd us of our <hi>Fear!</hi> And be only in <hi>Fear</hi> now of wronging the Mercy, by which we have been ſo ſweetly Reliev'd, and ſo greatly Oblig'd.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Advantages</hi> which this Peace brings us, are for both Worlds; And (1.) For the <hi>Preſent.</hi> You are at Liberty now, My Brethren, to Enjoy your Own, And may look upon it as <hi>Yours,</hi> and take En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to Till your Lands, and follow your Trades; As hoping that you ſhall inherit the Benefit; and not Labour only for Others; nor have the Bread which you have Earn'd, Snatch'd out of your Mouths; But ſee <hi>Peace,</hi> as the Root, producing the Fruits of <hi>Plenty:</hi> For <hi>making Peace in our Borders,</hi> is a Means to <hi>fill us with the fineſt of the Wheat,</hi> Pſal. 147.14. And after <hi>Peace be within thy Walls,</hi> follows, <hi>Proſperity be within thy Palaces,</hi> Pſal. 122.7. When every one may purſue their Occaſions without Diſturbance; And not be taken off, for the Defence of their Country, nor
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29883:7"/>Plunder'd by Soldiers, nor fall a Prey to Pyrates, nor be Eaten up by the Enemies, that lay all Deſolate. For what a ſad and fearful <hi>Community</hi> of Goods is made by <hi>War,</hi> that leaves no Property, but what can be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by the <hi>Longeſt</hi> Sword, and the <hi>Strongeſt</hi> Arm! But <hi>Peace</hi> ſets a Fence about your Poſſeſſions, and makes better Intrenchments and Fortifications in your Defence, than what can be rais'd by the biggeſt Armies, and multitudes of Pioneers. Now Seas are Open, and Commerce on the Wheels; and Men put in <hi>Heart,</hi> to uſe their <hi>Hands,</hi> and beſtir themſelves with Courage and Alacrity; in promoting their Concerns, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing themſelves, and all their Appurtenances, as a Proſperous and Happy People. Thus for the <hi>Preſent</hi> World. And</p>
            <p n="2">2. Peace gives great Advantages, (if it be well us'd) for the <hi>World to come;</hi> To make Religion, as well as Trading, Thrive and Flouriſh; To give <hi>Rulers</hi> Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Opportunity, better to Inſpect and Regulate their People at <hi>Home,</hi> when their Thoughts and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are not ſo Engag'd and taken up <hi>Abroad;</hi> To ſet themſelves againſt the <hi>Inteſtine</hi> Domeſtick Enemies, The Atheiſm and Impiety, The Profaneneſs and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery, that occaſion ſuch Pangs and Convulſions in the Bowels of the Nation; And threaten us with Worſe things yet from an Angry <hi>God,</hi> than any have befallen us from the hands of <hi>Man.</hi> And truly, if there be no <hi>Healing</hi> here, there will be yet no Remedy, but our Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after all, muſt be <hi>Miſery.</hi> If we cannot forbear to <hi>Fight</hi> with Him, that makes our Enemies at <hi>Peace</hi> with us; If we muſt ſtill, in our Oaths and Curſes, and all our Ungodly Provoking Carriage, Let fly at <hi>Heaven,</hi> after we have got the <hi>Peace</hi> on Earth; and turn the richeſt Bleſſing all to Pride and Wantonneſs, to Luxury and Riot; and requite the Lord that has done
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29883:8"/>all for us, only with <hi>Drinking</hi> the Deeper, and <hi>Swearing</hi> the Faſter; Will the Righteous and Jealous God En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it? And will he not be <hi>Avenged on ſuch a People as this?</hi> Let 'em be never ſo Frolick and Jocund at the <hi>Peace,</hi> alas, There's no <hi>Peace</hi> to them. They are quite out, and all to Pieces with the God of Heaven: And inſtead of any Healing, they do but make the matter ſtill worſe and worſe; And all their preſent Quiet and Proſperity, is but a little <hi>Calm</hi> and Sunſhine, before the moſt dreadful <hi>Storm; Fire and Brimſtone, a horrible Tempeſt, and the Blackneſs of Darkneſs,</hi> which they muſt Endure for ever.</p>
            <p>But it is to another End, that God ſends us <hi>Peace,</hi> Beloved, To engage us to be <hi>Better;</hi> and not Embolden us to go all to <hi>Naught.</hi> The Deſign of Heaven, in Saving us from our <hi>Enemies,</hi> and from the hands of them that <hi>Hate</hi> us, You have often heard from <hi>Luke</hi> I. 71, 74, 75. <hi>That we might Serve our Lord, without Fear,</hi> (of them) <hi>In Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him, all the days of our Life:</hi> That we ſhould Reſent his Kindneſs in Grateful Hearts, and Sing his <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and cheerfully Devote our ſelves to his <hi>Worſhip;</hi> And ſet it in our Hearts to Live <hi>Holily</hi> unto him, that has ſo abundantly Obliged us; Thus ſhewing the good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Uſe we make of his Benefits, That we do not Forget what he has done, and what we have to do; and that we dare not Rebel againſt him, with his own <hi>Indulgence</hi> to us; But Abhor ſo fouly to Misbehave our ſelves towards him, after all the ſweet <hi>Engagements</hi> his Love has laid upon us.</p>
            <p>And O what Encouragement have we now to Serve our God in the Gladneſs of our Hearts, when he has Rais'd our <hi>Sinking</hi> State, and ſo Secur'd our <hi>Hazardous</hi> Effects! when he has a new Confirm'd to us the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of all our dear Enjoyments, and anſwer'd us even in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29883:8"/>the Wiſhes of our Hearts! When he has given us the thing that we Long'd for, and <hi>Bleſs'd his People with Peace;</hi> When the <hi>Dread</hi> is remov'd that Chill'd our Spirits, and Shrunk up the Powers of our Souls; When our Minds are at Reſt, and an overflowing Tide of Joy <hi>Dilates</hi> and enlarges our Hearts! Then we have the inviting Opportunity ſet before us, to ſerve our Lord with <hi>Gladneſs;</hi> and to make a worthy <hi>Progreſs</hi> in his Holy ways; when we have nothing to Interrupt and Annoy us; no Concern of <hi>Invading</hi> Armies to fill our Heads, and Diſtract our Thoughts: Then, not only the Obligation is laid upon our <hi>Ingenuity,</hi> to expreſs our Thankfulneſs to the Lord of Love, in ways meet for his Acceptance; But a <hi>Price</hi> is alſo put into our hands, to be Improved for the Glory of our great <hi>Deliverer;</hi> that we ſhould chearfully Abound in his Work, and addict our ſelves to advance the Intereſts of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, together with our own Salvation; And in Living to his Praiſe, Finiſh our courſe with Joy. And thus we may make the preſent <hi>Peace</hi> Subſervient to our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Bliſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But one Conſideration more we have to heighten our Pleaſure in this <hi>Peace,</hi> and our Thankfulneſs for it; That the God of <hi>Peace</hi> ſends it to us by the Royal Hands of ſuch a Great and Worthy <hi>Meſſenger;</hi> The only Perſon upon Earth, whom he Inſpir'd with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and Fortitude and Reſolution ſufficient, to <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard</hi> his Life, and all that he had in the World for our Relief. O how <hi>Beautiful</hi> were his <hi>Feet,</hi> coming to our Land, juſt as we lay upon the <hi>Block,</hi> under the Sacrificing <hi>Knife!</hi> Then we receiv'd him even as an <hi>Angel of God,</hi> and thought we could never enough Admire the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of ſuch a Seaſonable and Bleſſed <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> And though the Difficulty of our Affairs was ſuch, as Engaged him to go with the Sword in his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29883:9"/>Hand, for theſe <hi>thrice Three</hi> Years now paſt: Yet has he Convinced the World, that the <hi>War</hi> he wag'd was not for <hi>War's</hi> ſake; but to bring the Enemies at laſt to this Honourable <hi>Peace.</hi> And hereby he has given a Demonſtration to all Men, of his Wiſe <hi>Conduct,</hi> and his mighty <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and Heaven's <hi>Bleſſing</hi> upon both; to accompliſh the thing which look'd ſo Improbable to come to paſs.</p>
            <p>And now that God has given him his <hi>Quietus</hi> from the Toil and <hi>Fatigue</hi> of Arms, and Reſtored him to us in Safety, according to our Prayers, To give <hi>Reſt</hi> to his People, and Diſmiſs 'em from the <hi>Military</hi> Attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; To mind every one the Concerns of his own private <hi>Good,</hi> and to rejoyce altogether in the Publick Gladneſs of the <hi>Nation;</hi> O how <hi>Beautiful</hi> are the Feet of ſuch a Meſſenger of <hi>Peace,</hi> upon the <hi>Mountains</hi> of ſuch Hazards as he has gone over, and ſuch ſeeming <hi>Impoſſibilities</hi> in the way, that he has <hi>Surmounted;</hi> and all the Pains that he has been at to make us <hi>Eaſy!</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, that has brought him back, not only Safe, but in <hi>Peace;</hi> and the Reſtorer of <hi>Peace</hi> to us; The Repairer of our Breaches, The Aſſertor of our Rights, The Preſerver of our Liberties, and, under God, The <hi>Defender</hi> of our Faith and Life!</p>
            <p>O may the ſame God Inſpirit and Enable him, to do yet a <hi>Greater</hi> Work among us! After all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown of his Signalized Valour in the <hi>Field,</hi> That he may ſhew the beſt of Courage at <hi>Home,</hi> A holy Zeal for Him, by whom <hi>Kings do Reign;</hi> In Mawling and breaking to pieces, The <hi>Leviathans,</hi> the <hi>Serpents,</hi> the wild <hi>Boars</hi> and <hi>Bears,</hi> All the Herd of various Bruits and <hi>Beaſts of the people,</hi> that Combine and make In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, to Aſſault our holy <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> ſome to Poyſon the Very <hi>Fountains</hi> of Life and Salvation, To Unhinge all the Doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and Ridicule
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29883:9"/>the Faith of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> as an idle Fancy: And more of 'em to Trample down all Godly, Righteous, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Converſation; To ſtrike at the Holy One him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and make a <hi>Party</hi> to Strengthen the hands of the Wicked, and to <hi>Out brave</hi> all ſerious Piety, and ſet up a Licentious <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Practice in its Room. O! here is a Courage worthy the <hi>Man of God's Right Hand,</hi> the moſt Puiſſant King, and all the Powers Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd of God; to be ſhewn, in Taming, Reducing or Suppreſſing theſe Monſters of Mankind, theſe Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant Bruits, and Incarnate Fiends; The Blaſphemous <hi>Swearers,</hi> The Beaſtly <hi>Drunkards,</hi> The Lewd <hi>Epicures,</hi> The Lawleſs <hi>Libertines,</hi> The Roaring <hi>Crew,</hi> that ſet God and his holy Religion at Defiance. O how much would it add to the Joy and Triumphs of this Day, (As to hear of all our Proteſtant Brethren Abroad Sharing with us therein, So) to ſee a Mighty Victory here; and ſuch <hi>Wickedneſs of the Wicked</hi> brought to an <hi>End;</hi> Such da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Impiety, and notorious Immorality driven to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and Baniſht the Nation! And to ſee thoſe Pious and Amiable <hi>Societies,</hi> (Erected and Engag'd, by Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Stipulations among themſelves, to promote the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Manners,</hi>) that in ſome Places have done very great and Worthy things already, Encouraged and Strengthned, every where, to do ſtill <hi>more</hi> and <hi>Better!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will hope, That ſo Excellent a <hi>Prince</hi> as God has Raiſed up, and Impowered to do ſuch Wonders for his Church and People, will not be wanting here; Now eſpecially, that he has a <hi>Vacation</hi> from the Foreign <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditions;</hi> and by his Reſidence amongſt us, will have fairer Opportunities, to turn and <hi>Exert</hi> his Courage, where it is moſt Needful to be ſhewn: And (as <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhua</hi> exhorted the Elders and Heads and Judges and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Chap. 23.6.) <hi>Be very Courageous</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29883:10"/>mote all Holy Obedience to the Will and Commands of God. And they muſt be <hi>Valiant</hi> indeed, that dare Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for God, and his Goſpel-Truth, and holy Cauſe, in the face of an <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> and <hi>Licentious</hi> Age. This is a <hi>Courage</hi> highly Neceſſary to Stem the Tide, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Courſe of this preſent Evil World. A Courage that will, (it's true) make him Formidable to the <hi>Evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers:</hi> But thoſe very <hi>Feet</hi> which Tread them down, will be more <hi>Beautiful</hi> ſtill in the eyes of all Enlightned Souls. Yea ſuch <hi>Contending</hi> with the Wicked, is the way of making <hi>Peace</hi> with Heaven: And by this means he will bring us Tidings of a better <hi>Peace</hi> yet than the preſent. Of which I am next to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>And I have prevented my Self, for ſaying much up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Head; by my Late Diſcourſes here of the <hi>Peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A Peace that takes up the Offenſive Matters, and ends the Quarrel between the <hi>Holy God</hi> and <hi>Sinful</hi> man. But the terms of this <hi>Peace,</hi> are not in any Writings of the <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> No, nor in the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> to be found. 'Tis only the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of our Lord that Acquaints us with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our <hi>Peace;</hi> This <hi>Peace</hi> with God through the Faith of Jeſus, The great <hi>Plenipotentiary</hi> of Heaven, Sent not only to <hi>Treat</hi> with us, but to Effect the Bleſſed <hi>Peace</hi> for us. And O how <hi>Beautiful</hi> are his <hi>Feet,</hi> that bring <hi>Reſt</hi> to the Labouring and heavy-Laden <hi>Souls!</hi> To all that Believe how <hi>Precious</hi> is He, and <hi>Altogether Lovely!</hi> Though <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſome among ourſelves, that Name the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (But are little better Friends, and can deal even as <hi>Jewiſhly</hi> with him) See no <hi>Form or Comelineſs or Beauty in him, for which they ſhould De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him;</hi> Yet never a true Chriſtian in the World, that does not account all things as <hi>Loſs, for the excellency of the Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus his Lord.</hi> Such have all their <hi>Rejoicing</hi> in him; but <hi>no Conſidence in the Fleſh.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29883:10"/>Phil.</hi> 3.3. No, They dare not Truſt to that for their <hi>Peace,</hi> which can never procure their <hi>Pardon.</hi> But when Chriſt is <hi>our Peace.</hi> Eph. 2. 14. and has <hi>made Peace through the Blood of his Croſs.</hi> Col. 1.20. 'Tis only that Blood which <hi>Satisfies</hi> for their Sins, which can <hi>Pacify</hi> their Conſciences. And when our Lord has told us, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. laſt ver. <hi>In me you ſhall have Peace:</hi> They are wretched Chriſtians, and miſerable Comforters, that would <hi>Seduce</hi> us, to go and Seek it elſewhere, and drive us out of this Beſt and only <hi>Refuge</hi> for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Soul; Even the Righteouſneſs and Satisfaction, The Merits and Interceſſion of our great <hi>Redeemer;</hi> Which is all the Hope and Support, The ſure Hold and Everlaſting Conſolation of all that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the Goſpel way of finding <hi>Reſt</hi> for their Souls! And whoever would know the things of their <hi>Peace,</hi> e're they be <hi>Hid</hi> from their eyes; They muſt quit all other <hi>Pleas</hi> and Confidences in the World; and be glad to caſt Anchor here, and Truſt their <hi>All</hi> in this <hi>Bottom.</hi> For he that <hi>Believeth not,</hi> (whatever elſe he does) <hi>The Wrath of God abideth on him.</hi> But <hi>whoſoever Believes on the Name of the Son of God, ſhall not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life.</hi> Joh 3.16. and laſt <hi>Verſe.</hi> 'Tis only by the <hi>Merit</hi> of his Blood, that we have our <hi>Pardon:</hi> and therefore only by <hi>Faith</hi> in the ſame Blood, that we can have our <hi>Peace.</hi> 'Tis this Heavenly <hi>Balm</hi> alone that can Cure the Diſeaſed Mind. And this is (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) the <hi>Glad Tidings</hi> of the Goſpel; To <hi>Preach Peace by Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of all.</hi> Acts 10.36. <hi>By him is Preached the Forgiveneſs of Sins: and by him all that Believe are Juſtified from all things, from which they could not be Juſtified by the Law of Moſes.</hi> Acts 13.38, and 39.</p>
            <p>And this it is that makes him ſo Dear and <hi>Precious</hi> to all Believers; And his <hi>Feet,</hi> even upon <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29883:11"/>(White and Red with his Innocence and Sufferings) So <hi>Beautiful</hi> in their eyes: Becauſe they <hi>Trod the Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs of Gods Wrath alone;</hi> and bore all that, which elſe muſt have fallen on the Sinners themſelves, to Sink 'em for ever. And this alſo makes even the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Miniſters,</hi> ſent by this great <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of Heaven, ſo Welcome to all his Faithful People: Becauſe they come upon the like Errand, To Proclaim their <hi>Peace</hi> with God, through <hi>Faith</hi> in his Blood. For to the Miniſters of Chriſt S. <hi>Paul</hi> applies this very Text; <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>How Beautiful are the Feet of them that preach the Goſpel of Peace, and bring Glad Tidings of Good things!</hi> Their <hi>Feet</hi> (importing their Divine Miſſion, and their Fervor in delivering the Will of their Lord) are commended here, not ſo much for their Strength or Nimbleneſs, as their <hi>Beauty:</hi> Becauſe they Draw Men to the Faith of Chriſt, not with <hi>Dread</hi> or <hi>Force;</hi> but with the Sanctity of Life, the Sweetneſs of Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the Power of their Doctrine. And they come upon the <hi>Mountains</hi> too; Through great Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the way of their Miniſtry; where ſo many withſtand 'em; and the <hi>Devil</hi> often raiſes Perſecution againſt 'em. Yet nothing ſhall ſtop 'em; But they will <hi>Publiſh</hi> the Goſpel to all, and lay the Salvation of their Lord in <hi>Common:</hi> That every one whom they can poſſibly prevail with, may enjoy the Bleſſed Benefit. And therefore to the <hi>Faithful</hi> none are ſo Gracious and Amiable: None whom they more Admire, or have a greater Veneration and Affection for. They Receive 'em as the <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> of the King of Glory: and cry, like the <hi>Damſel,</hi> Acts 16.17. <hi>Theſe men are the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the moſt High God, who ſhew to us the way of Salvation.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o high an Honour and ſingular Kindneſs have they for 'em, They could, (as the A poſtle ſpeaks, Gal. 4.15. <hi>if poſſible) even pluck out their own Eyes,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29883:11"/>to give 'em to their Preachers, Yea for their <hi>Lives,</hi> (like <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila,</hi> Rom. 16.3.) they could <hi>lay down their own Necks.</hi> So Surprizing, ſo Joyful is the News of <hi>Everlaſting Salvation</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt to poor <hi>Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Sinners; That they think they can never ſufficiently expreſs their Gratitude, their Reſpects, their Cordial Inclination to the <hi>Dear Meſſengers</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>But Wicked and Worldly men are not ſo fond of 'em. They give 'em but a very Cold Reception, if not the Rough Handling; and would more Thank 'em to be <hi>Quiet,</hi> than to Deliver their <hi>Meſſage.</hi> They Deſpiſe 'em, as Impertinent Buſy-bodies; Yea they Reſiſt 'em, as the <hi>Troublers of Iſrael.</hi> And whoever will adventure to do as God commands him, that is, <hi>Cry aloud, and not Spare:</hi> Muſt expect to be called, <hi>A man of Strife and Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> Though he be never ſo Fair in his Carriage, and have no <hi>perſonal</hi> Quarrel with any one in the World. They Except not only againſt our <hi>Preaching,</hi> but our very <hi>Calling;</hi> as Supervaneous, and a Nuiſance to the World. And indeed one that meant to be Faithful in it, would never meddle with the <hi>Thankleſs</hi> Office, among ſuch Ill-willers to the Lord's Meſſengers; But chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be a contemptible Dunghil-raker, than a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Impartial <hi>Miniſter;</hi> To be Scorn'd and Huff'd by Lordly Sinners, and nothing but <hi>Maligned</hi> and ſtruck at by the Conſcious Offenders: Were we not aſſur'd, That our <hi>Judgment were with the Lord, and our Work with our God:</hi> And did we not hope for infinitely bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Rewards, than their <hi>Good Graces;</hi> Who can Quarrel the very Meſſage of <hi>Peace;</hi> Becauſe it does not include a <hi>Peace</hi> for them with all their <hi>Sins:</hi> Becauſe it Rouzes their Worldly <hi>Neſts;</hi> and will not ſuffer 'em here to ſet up their <hi>Reſt;</hi> Nor <hi>Bolſter</hi> 'em up in all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs and Libertiniſm, wherein they are Reſolved to Perſiſt. The very <hi>Goſpel</hi> it ſelf is an Offence; and then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29883:12"/>no wonder, if its <hi>Miniſters</hi> be an Eye-ſore to 'em. A Lewd Ungodly Sinner thinks he has not a worſe <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> than a Sound and Zealous <hi>Preacher.</hi> No, for ſuch do find him out, and put him to <hi>Shame,</hi> and fill him with Dread. They are his Diſturbers, his Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: He cannot Love, He does not like 'em. He could wiſh 'em all utterly Silenc'd. His Conſcience cannot Sleep for their <hi>Barking.</hi> Away with 'em; They put him out of Patience; They drive him even to his Wits end. Their Meſſage, how Sweet and Reliſhing ſoever to ſome, 'tis to him nothing but the <hi>Burden of the Lord;</hi> All Briars and Thorns. A heavy Doleful Story, too Grievous for him to Bear it. He Complains, as the Man did of the <hi>Delphick Oracle,</hi> You never give a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable</hi> Anſwer. But the <hi>Oracle</hi> reply'd, You never come to me till your Caſe is paſt <hi>Remedy.</hi> And may not Chriſt's Miniſters ſo tell the Agrieved Sinner? You run your Soul upon <hi>Deſperate</hi> Streights; and ſtill keep up your Rebellion againſt Heaven: And then you are angry, That we will not Preach <hi>Peace,</hi> and Prophecy none but <hi>Smooth things;</hi> when alas, No ſuch things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to you. And then is it your Miniſters Fault or Yours, if nothing but Speaking <hi>Lyes</hi> will Pleaſe you, and that which <hi>Obliges</hi> all the Generation of God's Children, <hi>Offends</hi> you? If you will Out-run your own Mercies, and nothing but make <hi>Rods</hi> for your ſelves, O how can we help your Trouble? We would be as Glad to <hi>Speak Peace,</hi> as you to <hi>Hear</hi> it: For that is our Meſſage; and it Grieves us, when we cannot give you a Share in it. But yet we dare not <hi>Speak</hi> it, where the <hi>Lord</hi> has not Spoken it; Yea where he has <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden</hi> it, and Threatned us, with <hi>Woe</hi> to us, If we Harden the Wicked, and <hi>Strengthen</hi> him in his Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by <hi>Promiſing him Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29883:12"/>
            <p>But Reaſon as we will, The prejudicate Caviller al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges <hi>Reaſon,</hi> for Refuſing the Meſſengers that come to him in the name of the <hi>Lord.</hi> Their <hi>Feet</hi> are <hi>Dirty,</hi> and far from <hi>Lovely.</hi> Their Affections are <hi>Earthly,</hi> and all for the World: And their Converſations are <hi>Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,</hi> or at beſt no more than <hi>Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is our Accuſation; And we are ſorry, That there is too much <hi>Truth</hi> in the Charge. We Confeſs it; We Bewail it; We beg Pity and Pardon from God and Man for it. We have the <hi>Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels;</hi> And our Hearts hang too Near the <hi>Ground;</hi> And our Lives are too <hi>Diſſonant</hi> from the holy Goſpel which we preach. But then let me tell you, my Brethren, That you may gather <hi>Conſolation,</hi> even from that, which is the Matter of our <hi>Humiliation;</hi> That the moſt High God is pleas'd to Speak to you, by men of <hi>like Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with yourſelves:</hi> Which is a Favour from the Lord, that his People of old were very Importunate for, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.19. <hi>They ſaid unto Moſes, Speak thou with us, and we will hear: But let not God ſpeak with us, leſt we dye.</hi> If then we are no more than Ordinary men, yet you are to own it, as an Extraordinary Mercy from God, That he will graciouſly Vouchſafe to Treat with you by your <hi>Peers.</hi> And inſtead of Diſdaining us, for <hi>our Weakneſs;</hi> It will beſeem you to Thank him for <hi>his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> To ſhew you Hopes of Salvation, on this ſide that <hi>Perfection,</hi> which is not Attained even by thoſe, whom he Sends to Call and invite others to <hi>Aſpire</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. And where you cannot ſee any Recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in us; Yet let us find ſome fair Reception, for our <hi>Commiſſion</hi> Sake, for our <hi>Meſſage</hi> Sake, and for your <hi>Souls</hi> Sake. Seeing your Salvation is Concern'd in our Application. For we <hi>Publiſh Salvation; and ſay unto Zion, Thy God Reigneth.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29883:13"/>
            <p>Whether his <hi>Salvation</hi> ſhall openly Appear yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>End</hi> of the World, and his Kingdom Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſhew it ſelf here upon <hi>Earth;</hi> We cannot tell: We dare not Determine. What God can do, We know; (As Improbable as ever things may look.) But what he will do, To Advance his Church above all, even in the Eye of this World; We leave in the Secrets of his Councel. Who knows, Whether after all the great <hi>Turns</hi> of Affairs that we have <hi>Seen;</hi> there will not yet be a greater <hi>Turn,</hi> than ever the World <hi>Saw?</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may not expect yet a further Compleating of that Prophecy, Iſa. 2.2. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs in the Laſt days, That the Mountain of the Lord's houſe ſhall be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Top of the Mountains, and ſhall be Exalted above the Hills: And all Nations ſhall Flow to it.</hi> And as one Effect of that Glorious Change, it is ſaid, <hi>Ver.</hi> 4. They ſhall alter the property of their Martial In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, <hi>and not Learn War any more.</hi> But Antipathies ſhall be Reconciled; and the moſt Noxious Creatures <hi>ſhall not Hurt nor Deſtroy in all his Holy Mountain. Chap.</hi> 11.9. And he knows in what Senſe that has been, or ſhall be fulfilled, which the Lord ſhew'd to his Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Servant S. <hi>John</hi> in Viſion; Rev. 21.2. <hi>The Holy City, New Jeruſalem coming down from God out of Heaven, prepared as a Bride Adorned for her Husband.</hi> The Glorious things ſpoken of the <hi>City of God</hi> (there and in the Prophets) ſeem to want a further <hi>Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment</hi> even in this World, than ever yet has been. However, we may be bold to take up <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 8.12. <hi>Surely I know it ſhall go well with them that Fear God, that Fear before him.</hi> So Himſelf has bid us Aſſure 'em; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Say ye to the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, It ſhall be well with them.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 32.17, 18. <hi>The Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the Effect of Righteouſneſs Quietneſs, and Aſſurance for ever. And
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29883:13"/>my People ſhall dwell in a Peaceable Habitation, and in Sure Dwellings, and in quiet Reſting places.</hi> They have, long time, ſeem'd to have the <hi>Worſt:</hi> But in the Iſſues of things they ſhall, for certain, have the <hi>Beſt</hi> of it; and be the <hi>Riſing People</hi> after all; To <hi>Reign</hi> with Chriſt, and Sit <hi>Enthron'd</hi> in his Kingdom. Yea their Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with their Redemption, is drawing <hi>Nigh.</hi> And while they Look to the <hi>Faithful</hi> and <hi>True,</hi> that has Promiſed, Waiting for the <hi>Salvation of God;</hi> They ſhall not be <hi>Aſhamed</hi> of their Hope; But find all turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Favour, to make 'em Great and Glorious for ever. For they are the <hi>Temple of the Living God: As God hath ſaid, I will Dwell in them, and Walk in them: And I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.16. <hi>Thy God reigneth,</hi> Carries all in it. For if he be <hi>Ours,</hi> we are <hi>His.</hi> And when he ſhews Himſelf, <hi>Like Himſelf,</hi> We ſhall then be alſo <hi>Like him;</hi> And not only <hi>Gaze</hi> on, but <hi>Share</hi> in, his Glory.</p>
            <p>For our part, As the beſt <hi>Preparation</hi> to this Future <hi>Salvation,</hi> Let us be in care to Secure to our ſelves ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Salvation</hi> at preſent: That is, To be Saved from our <hi>Sins,</hi> and from the Love and courſe of this preſent evil World. O let us Hearken and Yield to the <hi>Goſpel of Peace,</hi> and take the way that it puts us upon, to make our <hi>Agreement</hi> with Heaven; and Cloſe up our <hi>Peace</hi> with God, in this day of Grace. And then we may comfortably look for Better things, than any we are able now to Deſcribe or Imagine. And whatever be the <hi>Manner</hi> of the Coming of our Lord's Kingdom, we may be ſure, That <hi>Come</hi> it ſhall: And when it Comes, put every Penitent Believing Soul into Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch Bleſſed Unſpeakable Attainments, as no <hi>Eye</hi> hath Seen, nor <hi>Ear</hi> Heard, nor any <hi>Heart</hi> of Man can Conceive.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29883:14"/>
            <p>And now that <hi>the moſt High who Rules in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of men,</hi> has been pleas'd to give us ſome <hi>Preludi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> of what may be hereafter; and a joyful <hi>Specimen</hi> of his Over-ruling Power, in <hi>Faſhioning all the Hearts of the Sons of men;</hi> and bringing the moſt Diſtant and Divided cloſe together: Now that after all the Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Preparations, and Hoſtilities, <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> have kindly Met, and Shaken Hands, and Struck up a Happy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> And the Gracious Lord has not only Exceeded our <hi>Hopes,</hi> but his own <hi>Promiſe;</hi> To <hi>make our Enemies at Peace with us,</hi> Though our <hi>Ways</hi> have not been <hi>Pleaſing</hi> to him. O how ſhall we receive the Kindneſs ſent from Heaven! And how ſhall we uſe the <hi>Peace</hi> granted on Earth! Shall we fall into their <hi>Abſurdity,</hi> who are <hi>Sullen,</hi> and little Pleas'd, That God has done us Good againſt their <hi>Wills?</hi> Or ſhall we run into their Extravagance, who know not how to expreſs their <hi>Tranſports,</hi> but in the Wantonneſs of <hi>Bruits</hi> full Fed, or the Wildneſs of <hi>Heathens</hi> running Mad? Shall we go on to Kick at our only Friend? To <hi>Grieve</hi> his Spirit, that has <hi>Eas'd</hi> ours, and prepare for <hi>Battel</hi> with him, who has given us <hi>Peace?</hi> God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, We ſhould ſo <hi>Thank</hi> him, for Sparing and Saving us. God forbid, We ſhould ſhew ſuch Curſed <hi>Fruits</hi> of all the precious <hi>Seed</hi> he has Sown amongſt us: Like a People not only <hi>Fooliſh and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwiſe,</hi> but <hi>Incorrigible and Deſperate.</hi> But if any Goodneſs will <hi>Oblige</hi> us; If the deareſt Love and Mercy will <hi>Win</hi> us; O let that which <hi>God, even our own God,</hi> has now done for us, Gain upon us, and Prevail with us; To throw down the <hi>Arms</hi> that we have taken up againſt Heaven, The Known Wilful <hi>Sins,</hi> that bid Defiance to our Maker and our Judge: And be <hi>Reconciled</hi> unto God, Seek his <hi>Peace,</hi> Keep in his <hi>Love,</hi> Live to his <hi>Honour,</hi> and alſo in ſuch good Underſtanding and fair Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29883:14"/>with one another; That the God of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> may ſtill be with us; and Keep off all <hi>Evils</hi> from us, and Rejoice over us, to do <hi>Good</hi> to us; and never be Weary to Expreſs all his <hi>Kindneſs</hi> upon us.</p>
            <p>To him let us Lift up our <hi>Hearts,</hi> and make the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Ourſelves,</hi> together with our <hi>Thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Praiſe waiteth for thee, O God, in <hi>Zion:</hi> And in thy Temple ſhould every one ſpeak of thy Glory. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving entred thy Gates with Thankſgiving, and into thy Courts with Praiſe; We deſire to Continue the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of our Thanks, which is the due Tribute, that we come hither at this time to pay unto the God of our Lives, the Lord that has been ſo Favourable to our Land. For thou, Lord, haſt made us Glad through thy Work; we will Triumph in the Works of thy hands. Thou haſt been Mindful of us; Thou haſt been Good to us, and done great things for us; In making us a way to Eſcape out of the Fears and Dangers wherein our Sins involved us; Giving Reſt to thy People, and that Peace, which is the matter of our preſent Rejoycing before thee. According to thy Name, O Lord, ſo is thy Praiſe, to the Ends of the Earth. And above all the Nations of the Earth, are we Oblig'd to Magnify the Diſtinguiſhing Mercy of our God, who has ſhew'd us ſuch Marvellous Kindneſs, in a highly-favour'd Land; Turn'd away thy Anger and our Dread, Saved us from the Sword, Bleſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d thy People with Peace, and compaſs'd us about with Songs of Deliverance. Thou art our God, and we will Praiſe thee; Thou art our God, and we will Exalt Thee, and give Thanks to thy Name; and Rejoice in the Riches of thy Grace, and all the Wonders of thy Mercy to us. O that we may give thee the Glory due to thy Name! That not only our Tongues may ſpeak of thy Righteouſneſs and thy Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29883:15"/>But that our Souls may be Joyful in the Lord, and our Hearts ſo fixed, that in them we may make Melody; and Praiſe the Lord, with all our Hearts, and Glorify thy Name for evermore! Yea, as thou haſt given us Peace; So, we beſeech thee, Grant us thy Grace to Expreſs the Truth of our Thanks, By walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before thee all our days in the Uprightneſs of our Hearts: Devoting ourſelves, and all we are, and all that we Have, to Serve and Pleaſe our God, Through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom, with the Eternal Spirit, proceeding from Thee and thy Son, be Bleſſing, and Glory, and Wiſdom, and Honour, and Power, and Might, aſcrib'd by us, and by all the</hi> Iſrael <hi>of God, World without end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
